Okay, בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is י"ח Yud-Ches
and we take up with תא שמע, Tashma, second line from the
top. And to remind you, the question is, the issue is as
to whether a נזיר Nazir who starts off as a נזיר טמא,
Nazir tamei, who can only start his thirty days of counting towards
his נזירות nezirot when he becomes טהור, tahor, which is a seven-day
process because we're talking about טומאת מת, tumas meis, a טומאה tumah
with a dead body. So the question that is being has been
raised is whether that נזיר Nazir must shave on day seven. He
does not bring קרבנות korbanot on day eight because the קרבנות korbanot
as the משנה mishna said and as the גמרא gemara has been
saying are only when somebody starts off as טהור tahor and then
becomes טמא. tamei. We're going to actually see that in a minute,
the basis for that in the verse. So there's not going to
be any קרבן korban because he did not start off as טהור.
tahor.
So he will become so he will day seven will just be
a normal טהרה taharah process and he'll start his נזירות, nezirot, but
the question is even though he's not bringing קרבנות, korbanot, maybe he
still has to shave on
day seven. Which seems bizarre because normally we would assume the whole
rituals are bound together, which seems to be the inclination of the
גמרא. gemara. But something that is worth pointing out which we failed
to do yesterday is that the different days in which these rituals
are done. So actually let me just read those פסוקים psukim and
it says the following here from פרשת נשא Parshas Naso where the
גמרא gemara is going to quote these פסוקים psukim in a few
minutes: וכי ימות מת עליו בפתע פתאום, V'chi yamut meis alav befesa
pitom,
if a dead body dies on him suddenly, וטמא ראש נזרו, v'timei
rosh nizro, and the head of his נזירות nezirot became טמא—again, tamei
the focus on the hair—וגילח ראשו ביום טהרתו, v'gilach rosho b'yom taharato,
he shall shave his head on the day he becomes pure, ביום
השביעי יגלחנו, b'yom hashvi'i yiglachenu,
he shaves it on day seven. וביום השמיני, U'veyom hashmini, and on
day eight, יביא שתי תורים או שני בני יונה, yavi shtei torim
o shnei bnei yonah, he brings two turtledoves or two pigeons, whatever
whichever they are, אל הכהן אל פתח אהל מועד. el hakohen el
pesach ohel moed. ועשה הכהן אחד לחטאת ואחד לעולה, V'asah hakohen echad
l'chatas v'echad l'olah, one is a חטאת chatas and one is an
עולה, olah, וכפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש וקידש את ראשו ביום
ההוא, v'chiper alav m'asher chata al hanefesh v'kidesh es rosho bayom hahu,
he sanctifies his head that day, presumably day eight, we'll talk about
that. והזיר לה' את ימי נזרו, V'hizir l'Hashem es yemei nizro, he
shall dedicate to God the days of his נזירות, nezirot, והביא כבש
בן שנתו לאשם, v'hevi keves ben shnato l'asham, and bring an אשם,
asham, והימים הראשונים יפלו כי טמא נזרו, v'hayomim harishonim yiplu ki tamei
nizro, and the earlier days fall away because he has become טמא.
tamei. So there you see that the shaving of the head is
on day seven, not on day eight, and it's associated with becoming
טהור. tahor. So the גמרא, gemara, the question of the גמרא gemara
makes a lot more sense. Fine, he doesn't bring a קרבן, korban,
that's only when he started טהור tahor and became טמא. tamei. But
maybe there's a special הלכה halacha that the טהרה taharah process of
a נזיר Nazir or maybe in order to resume the נזירות nezirot
it requires this shaving. So even if he started as טמא, tamei,
maybe on day seven he has to do this shaving in order
to resume the נזירות. nezirot. So that's the question. So let's take
a look now as the גמרא gemara continues to address this and
we actually end this discussion with one very explicit ברייתא. braisa. תא
שמע Tashma come and hear, two lines from the top on י"ח
עמוד א': Yud-Ches Amud Aleph: וטמא ראש נזרו, v'timei rosh nizro, okay,
and the head of his נזירות nezirot becomes טמא, tamei, בטהור שנטמא
הכתוב מדבר. b'tahor she'nitma hakatuv midaber.
The verse is talking about a נזיר טהור Nazir tahor that became
טמא. tamei. That's when he has to bring a קרבן. korban. שטעון
העברת שיער והבאת ציפורין. Shetaun ha'avaras se'ar v'hava'as tziporin. Only such a
person requires
the shaving of the hair and the bringing of the bird. ופטר
את הנזיר בקבר. U'fatar es haNazir bakever. And this exempts, because it
speaks about his hair became טמא, tamei, which means it started טהור.
tahor. So that language of the verse excludes somebody who accepted his
נזירות nezirot when he was in a graveyard, שאין טעון העברת שיער
והבאת ציפורין, she'ein taun ha'avaras se'ar v'hava'as tziporin, that
that does not require shaving of the hair and the bringing of
the bird קרבנות. korbanot. והלא דין הוא, V'halo din hu, one minute,
says this ברייתא, braisa, you could have made a קל וחומר kal
vachomer to say it is required. ומה טהור שנטמא טעון העברת שיער
והבאת ציפורין, U'mah tahor she'nitma taun ha'avaras se'ar v'hava'as tziporin,
somebody who is טהור tahor who then became טמא tamei has to
do this whole process, מי שהיה טמא מתחילה אינו דין שיהיה טעון
העברת שיער והבאת ציפורין? mi shehayah tamei mitchilah eino din sheyiheh taun
ha'avaras se'ar v'hava'as tziporin?
Somebody who already started as טמא, tamei, I could say that's worse.
You never even got started on the right foot. You started as
טמא. tamei. How much more so maybe should this whole process be
required to now begin a נזירות nezirot of טהרה. taharah. If you
began it okay, then it's one thing to resume it. You never
began it okay, maybe you need a more you certainly should need
this process in order to begin a נזירות nezirot of טהרה. taharah.
I could have made that argument. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the
verse says, וטמא ראש נזרו. v'timei rosh nizro.
No, now his hair is his head, meaning he is becoming טמא.
tamei. במי שהיה טהור ונטמא הכתוב מדבר. B'mi shehayah tahor v'nitma hakatuv
midaber.
It's not a logical point, it's a point that that's the way
it's being described. Somebody that was טהור tahor and became טמא. tamei.
שיהיה טעון העברת שיער והבאת ציפורין. Sheyiheh taun ha'avaras se'ar v'hava'as tziporin.
Only that person requires the shaving of the hair and the bringing
of the birds. ופטר את הנזיר בקבר. U'fatar es haNazir bakever. And
to exempt the person who became a נזיר Nazir in the graveyard.
So like some earlier discussions, we had a whole long discussion yesterday
and the whole answer is very explicit in a ברייתא braisa black
and white. The whole process, whether it's the קרבנות korbanot and including
the shaving of the hair is only for somebody who started טהור.
tahor. Somebody who started טמא tamei becomes טהור tahor on day seven,
so a normal process of becoming טהור, tahor, and on day seven
begins the נזירות nezirot of טהרה taharah without any shaving of the
hair. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good proof.
Yes, isn't that a classic argument of if it were only logical,
you'd reach the other conclusion, but we have a פסוק pasuk and
interpret the פסוק pasuk contrary to what logic would dictate?
Well,
okay, I mean, the logic is not like logical that this was
the only conclusion. Often you could say ולא דין הוא, ve-lo din
hu, you could have made this argument, you could have made the
opposite argument, but it is very common in מדרשי הלכה midreshei halakhah
that this is like a very classic style of מדרש הלכה. midrash
halakhah. It says, here's the דרשה, derashah, here's what we learn out.
And then it takes a step back and says, wait, why do
we need the דרשה? derashah? Here's why we need the דרשה, derashah,
because if I was just left to having to try to figure
it out logically, I could have made the other argument. Okay, so
the דרשה derashah tells me don't. Now it is true that sometimes
מדרשי הלכה midreshei halakhah make the argument on both sides. It says,
you know, ולא דין הוא ve-lo din hu whatever it says, and
then it says או כלך לדרך הזה, o kelakh le-derekh hazeh, or
maybe I could have said the other way. So I could have
made an argument in both directions, the פסוק pasuk tells me this.
Here, it only makes the argument in one direction. I still don't
know if that would have meant that that would have dictated all
by itself, but yeah, that's the classic way the מדרש הלכה midrash
halakhah does it. It frames that if just מסברא, mi-sevara, you would
have been inclined to go one way or you could have gone
either way, and that's why you need the פסוק. pasuk. So that's
what we have. The פסוק pasuk tells me, and again, you know,
now that we read the פסוקים pesukim inside, we actually see that
the הוה אמינא hava amina wasn't as crazy as we thought. It's
very nice that the קרבן korban is day eight, but the shaving
is day seven, and that's where it's that's connected to becoming טהור,
tahor, and maybe that would have been required even without a קרבן.
korban. And it tells me no. Okay? If you start טמא, tamei,
you just do a normal טהרה taharah process, and on day seven
begin the נזירות nezirot of טהרה. taharah.
Can we safely say that a
פסוק pasuk trumps סברא?
sevara? Well, I'm not getting into that larger argument. I mean, the
גמרא Gemara sometimes says למה לי קרא סברא הוא, lama li kra
sevara hu, שבקיה לקרא דדחיק ואוקי אנפשיה. shavkieh le-kra de-dahik ve-uki anafsheih.
So I'm not going to get into that, that's a larger discussion.
Alright. מאן תנא הדתנו רבנן? man tanna ha-de-tannu rabanan? Who is the
תנא tanna of that which the rabbis taught?
אין בין טמא שנזר לנזיר טהור—we're ein bein tamei she-nazar le-nazir tahor
still on the same topic here—there's no difference between a טמא tamei
person who accepted נזירות nezirot and a טהור tahor person who was
a נזיר שנטמא Nazir shenitma. then became טמא, tamei, אלא שטמא שנזר
שביעי שלו עולה לו מן המנין, ela she-tamei she-nazar shevii shelo oleh
lo min ha-minyan, the one who began טמא tamei starts counting on
day seven. As we said, he just does a normal טהרה taharah
process, which is over on day seven, and then it begins. ונזיר
טהור שנטמא, ve-nazir tahor she-nitma, but if a person started off as
טהור tahor and became טמא, tamei, אין שביעי שלו עולה לו מן
המנין. ein shevii shelo oleh lo min ha-minyan. He does not start
on day seven, he only starts on day eight, because only day
eight is the bringing of the קרבנות. korbanot. Since he needs to
bring a קרבן, korban, he only resumes his process on day eight.
So that's what we've been saying all along. So now what the
גמרא Gemara is doing is, it knows we've been saying this all
along, but now it says, now that we've resolved some other discussions,
do you shave on day seven or not or is it whatever,
let's talk about this idea that a normal נזיר טהור nazir tahor
who became טמא tamei begins his new count on day eight. You
should know that although we've been assuming that and saying that all
along and quoting a lot of ברייתות Baraitot that say that, not
everybody agrees to that. So let's now point out that that's only
actually one opinion. Okay, so who is the תנא tanna that says
that? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב חסדא רבי היא. amar
Rav Hisda Rebbi hi. It's רבי. Rebbi. דאמר רבי, de-amar Rebbi, because
רבי Rebbi says, אין נזירות טהרה חלה עליו אלא עד שמיני, ein
nezirot taharah halah alav ela ad shemini, that the טהרה taharah process
for a normal נזיר nazir who becomes טמא tamei and then brings
a קרבן, korban, he only begins his thirty days of recounting starting
on day eight. Everything we've been assuming until now. דאי תימא רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, de-i teima Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehudah, because if you
would think it would be רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi
Yehudah, which you haven't even heard of until now, he, אמר נזירות
טהרה משביעי דחיילא. amar nezirot taharah mi-shevii de-hayla. But he actually says
a different opinion than we've been saying until now. He says that
even for a נזיר טהור nazir tahor that became טמא, tamei, the
classic נזיר nazir that became טמא, tamei, even though he brings his
קרבן korban on day eight, he begins his counting, his new נזירות,
nezirot, or his טהרה נזירות taharah nezirot on day seven, on the
day he became טהור. tahor. קרבן korban isn't relevant. He begins his
counting on day seven.
מאי רבי ומאי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? mai Rebbi u-mai Rabbi Yose
be-Rabbi Yehudah? So this is ultimately a way of saying, let me
introduce you now to this debate. Where do we see them debating
this? דתניא, de-tanya, in the following ברייתא: Baraita: וקידש את ראשו ביום
ההוא. ve-kiddash et rosho ba-yom ha-hu. Okay, he shall sanctify his head.
Now let me again read you where that appears in the פסוק.
pasuk. Okay, so the פסוק pasuk says again, it says,
וגלח ראשו ביום טהרתו ביום השביעי יגלחנו, ve-gilah rosho be-yom taharato ba-yom
ha-shevii yegalhenu, shave his hair on the day he becomes טהור tahor
on day seven. וביום השמיני, u-vayom ha-shemini, and the day eight, יביא
שתי תורים או שני בני יונה אל הכהן אל פתח אהל מועד,
yavi shetei torim o shenei benei yonah el ha-kohen el petah ohel
moed, you bring the קרבן, korban, these birds. ועשה הכהן אחד לחטאת
ואחד לעולה וכיפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש, ve-asah ha-kohen ehad le-hattat
ve-ehad le-olah ve-khipper alav me-asher hata al ha-nefesh, the כהן kohen brings
these sacrifices. וקידש את ראשו ביום ההוא. ve-kiddash et rosho ba-yom ha-hu.
The פסוק pasuk says, and he shall sanctify his head, meaning restart
the count on that day. So quick question: what day are we
talking about? Day seven or day eight? Day eight! We said day
seven you shave and you become טהור, tahor, day eight you bring
the... offers the קרבנות korbanos and כהן kohen offers the קרבנות korbanos
and you sanctify your head on that day. Very clearly day eight.
Let's see what רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi
Yehuda is saying. Okay. וקדש את ראשו ביום ההוא. Vekiddash es rosho
bayom hahu. ביום הבאת קרבנותיו, Beyom hava'as korbanosav, the day he brings
his קרבן, korban, דברי רבי, divrei Rebbi, that's what רבי Rebbi says.
רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi Yehuda אומר, omer,
no, ביום תגלחתו, beyom tiglachto, no, the other day, the earlier day
we were talking about, that day, not this day, that day, the
day we talked about before, day seven. Okay, very interesting interpretation. Okay.
והתנן, Vehatnan, that's what we taught, נזיר nazir שנטמא. she-nitma
We're going to in the end unpack that, like why he reads
ביום ההוא bayom hahu to be referring to an earlier day and
not the day we're talking about. But first we want to tie
this into another issue. והתנן, Vehatnan, we have a משנה. mishna. נזיר
שנטמא טומאות הרבה, Nazir shenitma tumos harbe, a נזיר nazir that became,
again, started טהור, tahor, became טמא, tamei, then became טהור tahor and
became טמא, tamei, became טהור tahor and became טמא, tamei, has many
of these acts of becoming טמא, tamei, and again after having become
טהור, tahor, נטמא טומאות הרבה nitma tumos harbe means became טמא tamei
from a state of being טהור. tahor. Okay. אינו מביא אלא קרבן
אחד. Eino mevi ella korban echad. Actually, it's possible to do that
multiple times and only have to bring one קרבן. korban. We're going
to see how that's possible in a minute, because each act should
have required another קרבן. korban. So מאן תנא, man tana, which of
these two תנאים, tanaim, רבי Rebbi or רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi Yehuda, does that go like? So אמר רב
חסדא רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה היא, Amar Rav Chisda Rebbi Yose
bar Rebbi Yehuda hi, it's רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yose
bar Rebbi Yehuda, דאמר נזירות דטהרה משביעי חיילה, de'amar neziros detahara mishvi'i
chayla,
that the נזירות neziros of טהרה tahara begins on day seven.
ומשכחת לה כגון שנטמא בשביעי וחזר ונטמא בשביעי, Umeshakchas lah k'gon shenitma
bishvi'i v'chozar v'nitma bishvi'i, that he became טמא tamei on day seven
and again on day seven. כיון דלא יצא שעה ראויה להביא קרבן,
Keivan delo yatza sha'ah re'uyah l'havi korban, since he did not yet
get to a stage where it's time to bring a קרבן, korban,
אינו חייב אלא קרבן אחד. eino chayav ella korban echad. He only
brings one קרבן. korban. So let me stop and unpack that, okay?
Which is, let's do it on the board. Never become טהור tahor
without the
זמן. zman.
Now the point is like this. You have to create a scenario
where you became טהור tahor and become טמא tamei again, right? Because
otherwise it's not an interesting point. If the guy kept on being,
staying in a graveyard for 30 days, or went out on day
one and back on day two, it's not an interesting point, of
course you only bring one קרבן. korban. The point is multiple successor
times he became טהור tahor and טמא, tamei, טהור tahor and טמא
tamei and only one קרבן. korban. So how's that going to be
possible? Shouldn't each thing require, obligate him in another קרבן? korban? So
the only way it's going to be possible is if when he
became טמא tamei again, he hadn't yet been חייב chayav in the
first קרבן. korban. Now how could he have not been חייב chayav
in the first קרבן? korban? Because although he was טהור tahor and
became טמא, tamei, it's understood that his חיוב chiyuv of the קרבן,
korban, in a way, the act on, he did the act that
would obligate him in the קרבן, korban, but the obligation only kicked
in when he got to day eight, when he got to the
day when it was possible to do it. So before day eight,
we said he is not yet obligated. He did the act, but
he is not yet obligated until day eight. Got the idea? So
here you got the guy, right? Here he is, he's טהור, tahor,
okay? He becomes טמא, tamei, okay? We're going to count seven days.
Okay, now here he has the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, right, day three and day seven. Okay, here
on day seven itself, you know this is day seven, okay? He
had the sprinkling, he is טהור, tahor, and then he becomes טמא
tamei again, okay? After having been טהור. tahor. Okay, so he was,
he was טהור tahor for a period in day seven, he became
טמא, tamei, that's multiple טומאות tumos from being טהור. tahor. He's not
yet obligated in a קרבן korban because the חיוב קרבן chiyuv korban
only kicks in on day eight, because he only brings the קרבן
korban on day eight. So therefore, because he hasn't yet gotten to
the day that he's חייב chayav in a קרבן, korban, he could
become טהור tahor and טמא tamei and then he could just keep
on repeating that ad infinitum without ever yet having been חייב chayav
in a קרבן. korban. All on day seven! All on day seven!
Now that only works according to רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yose bar Rebbi Yehuda, because רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה Rebbi Yose
bar Rebbi Yehuda would say that when, he doesn't only become טהור
tahor on day seven, he's now re-enter, enters into a state of
נזירות דטהרה. neziros detahara. He's now becoming and being a נזיר טהור,
nazir tahor, not just being טהור tahor for other הלכות halachos like
can he eat a קרבן, korban, right? Being טהור tahor as a
נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, the period of נזירות דטהרה neziros detahara begins
because according to רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yose bar Rebbi
Yehuda, you start counting your thirty days on day seven, the day
you became טהור. tahor. One second, but according to רבי, Rebbi, okay,
the גמרא's gemara going to say that even though he's טהור tahor
here, it would obviously, it would be an untrivial case, it would
be true, but it would be trivial to say that you would
only bring one קרבן korban if you became טהור tahor and טמא
tamei on day seven because you didn't even begin yet your נזירות
דטהרה. neziros detahara. So it's a trivial point. According to רבי, Rebbi,
the only interesting case is that would be worth talking about is
if you became טמא tamei on day eight. Your נזירות דטהרה neziros
detahara began and now you became טמא, tamei, now we could consider
that you would have to bring another, now we would think you'd
have to bring another קרבן. korban. Okay, but the problem is if
you became טהור tahor on day eight and then טמא, tamei, you
actually do have to bring another קרבן korban because you already became
חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. All right, so you got the
idea? That meaning for רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose be Rabbi
Yehuda, you have everything happened on day seven, you completely restarted the
whole process, you became טהור, tahor, you restarted the process of being
a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, and then you became טמא, tamei, so
everything is in place for you to become חייב chayav in a
second קרבן, korban, and the חידוש chidush is you're not, because you
haven't yet entered into day eight. But according to רבי, Rebbe, if
it happened on day seven it's trivial, and if it happened on
day eight it's false. Okay, so that's why רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yose be Rabbi Yehuda. I think you guys are in a
minute. Let's just read that final part of the statement for רבי.
Rebbe. Okay, so let's read it again: ומשכחת לה, umishkachat lah, we'll
start with ומשכחת לה, umishkachat lah, like the beginning of the line
about ten lines from the bottom.
ומשכחת לה כגון שנטמא בשביעי וחזר ונטמא בשביעי. umishkachat lah kegon shenitma
beshvii vachazar venitma beshvii. כיון דלא יצא שעה הראויה להביא קרבן, keivan
dela yatza shaah harauyah lehavi korban, since you have not entered into
a period where it's fit to bring a קרבן, korban, אינו חייב
אלא קרבן אחד, eino chayav ela korban echad, you're only חייב chayav
one קרבן korban because on day seven you became טהור, tahor,
everything restarted, and then you became טמא, tamei, and nevertheless here's an
amazing חידוש, chidush, you don't have to bring another קרבן korban because
you didn't yet enter day eight. אי אמרת רבי היא, ee amrat
Rebbe hee, because if it's רבי, Rebbe, so then again either it's
trivial or it's false. אי דנטמא בשביעי, ee denitma beshvii, if you
became טמא tamei on שביעי, shvii, so it's true, you did become
טהור, tahor, וחזר ונטמא בשביעי vachazar venitma beshvii like we sort of
set it up a minute ago, כולה טומאה אריכתא היא, kulah tumah
arichta hee, it's all one long טומאה. tumah. Now again, it doesn't
mean technically one long טומאה tumah because you did genuinely become טהור
tahor on day seven, right? The ashes were sprinkled, you became טהור,
tahor, but it's from the perspective of נזירות, nezirus, it's one ongoing
process because you did not yet begin the נזירות טהרה. nezirus taharah.
So it's a trivial point. Of course it's only one קרבן, korban,
you didn't begin your נזירות טהרה nezirus taharah yet on day seven.
ואי דנטמא בשמיני וחזר ונטמא בשמיני, ve-ee denitma beshmini vachazar venitma beshmini,
now if it happened on day eight and that's when you did
re-begin your נזירות טהרה, nezirus taharah, הרי יצא שעה הראויה להביא קרבן,
harei yatza shaah harauyah lehavi korban, so then it's incorrect, you are
obligated another קרבן korban because come day eight you're חייב chayav in
a קרבן. korban. So then if you became טמא tamei again after
being טהור, tahor, you would have to bring the second קרבן. korban.
So for רבי Rebbe it's either trivial or false, and only for
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be Rabbi Yehuda is it an
interesting case where day seven you became טהור, tahor, you restarted the
whole process, then you became טמא, tamei, so everything was restarted and
you became טמא tamei and nevertheless you don't bring another קרבן korban
because you never entered day eight so you never actually became obligated
in the first קרבן korban yet. Okay,
you had a question, right? All right, yes Charlie.
Okay, so I become טמא מת tamei meis and I do the
procedure, I get sprinkled, and on the seventh day I get sprinkled.
Am I really טהור tahor or am I a טבול יום? tevul
yom?
You're a טבול יום, tevul yom, but that's as תוספות Tosafos discussed
that yesterday, that's trivial for these purposes, it's not relevant. Okay, that
doesn't stand in the way of you becoming a נזיר טהור nazir
tahor and whatever, it's only something residual. Yes Sam.
Sure. So
the part in the brackets... doesn't make any sense to me because
how could you become pure on the same day again, right? It
makes it seem like how are you being, it seems like you're
this situation...
Which part are you going on where it says וחזר ונטמא? vachazar
venitma? Or מני רבי יוסי? Mani Rabbi Yose?
My question is you can't actually become pure again on day seven.
Yes you can. You sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah, you're טהור tahor on day seven. I mean Charlie's point is
you
need נטילה nitila again and then wait for the sun to set.
Yes. So that's just וחזר ונטמא vachazar venitma just telling you that
we can, however we set up the scenario,
we could just make it ad infinitum, right? If you can do
this twice you can do it three times and four times and
five times, right?
But it wouldn't be actually physically on the same day.
No, it's not this day שביעי, shvii, it's the next day שביעי.
shvii. Okay. Yes, Eli you had a question?
It was just a mathematical possibility of what would happen.
Yeah, exactly. We just like to set, okay. All right, so there
we've now laid out this really interesting debate. Until now, until today,
you were all thought, oh, he only starts his recount on day
eight when he brings his קרבן. korban. Now we find out that
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be Rabbi Yehuda says no, he
starts his נזירות טהרה nezirus taharah when he becomes טהור. tahor. He
has to bring a קרבן, korban, but his נזירות טהרה nezirus taharah
begins when he becomes טהור. tahor. And now the גמרא's Gemara tied
it into this interesting application of can you have multiple טומאות tumas
from something that's been fully restarted and still not bring multiple קרבנות.
korbanos. Okay, now we're going to go back and look at their
debate.
מאי טעמא דרבי? Mai taama de-Rebbe? What's the reason of רבי? Rebbe?
What do you mean what's the reason? It's pretty פשוט. pashut. אמר
קרא וכיפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש, amar kra vechipper alav measher
chata al hanafesh, since he atones for him so we're talking about
bringing the קרבנות, korbanos, could have also said it as ביום השמיני,
bayom hashmini, והדר כתיב וקידש את ראשו, vehadar ktiv vekiddash et rosho,
and then he resanctifies his head, which is understood to mean re-begins
the counting.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be Rabbi Yehuda would tell you,
אי הכי לימא קרא וקידש את ראשו, ee hachi leima kra vekiddash
et rosho, so just say that, just end with that. You bring
the קרבן korban and then you restart the counting. מאי ביום
ההוא למה לי? mai bayom hahu lama li? Why did you have
to add the extra two words "on that day"? So this is
one of those ironic cases where when the תורה Torah is more
specific, it's saying like you didn't have to say that. The fact
that you're being more specific means you're coming to say the opposite.
Okay, now of course it is interesting because you could say ביום
ההוא bayom hahu means "that day" as opposed to "this day," that
day that I was referring to earlier, but it's not פשט. pshat.
Okay, so ביום ההוא, bayom hahu, why do you have to say
ביום ההוא? bayom hahu? אם אינו ענין לשמיני, im eino inyan l'shmini,
you didn't need to tell me the eighth day. That's what we're
talking about. תנהו ענין לשביעי, tnehu inyan l'shvi'i, it must be talking
about day seven or else you wouldn't have bothered to say. You
could just imagine a kid trying to argue this with his father
or his mother. Well, you didn't have to say those extra two
words. You didn't have to say, I want you at home nine
o'clock, absolutely no later. Why'd you say absolutely no later? It must
have meant that really ten o'clock was okay. So
yes.
ביום השמיני. bayom hashmini.
Yeah, but I understand it's not the
פשט. pshat.
ביום השמיני יכפר עליו חטאת והיום הזה. bayom hashmini yechaper alav chatat
vehayom hazeh.
No, it's that day because it's that day from the perspective of
the narrator. There was no other way to say that, to say
that the day that you bring the קרבן. korban. You cannot say
ביום הזה. bayom hazeh. It would not have made any sense in
that context. Why? No, 'cause you're talking about, you're describing a different
scenario. You're not describing the case in front of you. It's always
that day, right? You can't say this day. The נזיר nazir will
bring his קרבן korban and he will resanctify his head on this
day. You can't say that. On that day, 'cause you're referring to
a different case than the one in front of you.
Anyway, alright, moving on, moving on. Okay. So that's what he says.
ביום ההוא bayom hahu is extra so it has to mean the
earlier day. It has to mean day seven. Okay. תנהו ענין לשביעי.
tnehu inyan l'shvi'i. That's what he says. Now, the פסוק pasuk aside,
you do understand a certain conceptual logic. Who needs to bring a
קרבן, korban, right? If he becomes טהור tahor on day seven, then
it should rekick in on day seven. That's when the count should
rekick in. Okay. ורבי נמי הכתיב. v'Rabbi nami hachtiv. But Rabbi also
it says ביום ההוא. bayom hahu. That's such a good point. These
extra words. So what is that teaching you? אמר לך רבי. amar
lach Rabbi. Rabbi will tell you, ההוא להכי הוא דאתא. hahu l'hachi
hu d'ata. No, here's what you use the ההוא hahu for. לומר
לך lomar lach to tell you, אף על פי שלא הביא קרבנותיו.
af al pi shelo heivi korbanotav. Ah, here's an interesting question
and this is what we're going to focus on for the remainder
of the דף daf or for a major section of it. What's
the story if it comes day eight and he is negligent in
bringing the קרבנות? korbanot? So is it just you restart on day
eight or you only restart after the קרבן korban is brought? Now
the פסוק pasuk sounds like after the קרבן korban is brought. You
bring the קרבן korban וכפר עליו vechiper alav and the כהן kohen
atones and then וקידש את ראשו. v'kidesh et rosho. But Rabbi says
no, that's the חידוש chidush of ביום ההוא. bayom hahu. ביום ההוא
bayom hahu means on that day even if you didn't bring the
קרבנות. korbanot. At least that's a better פשט pshat in the פסוק.
pasuk. Okay, but that's an interesting חידוש. chidush. Now you only need
day eight, you don't actually need the קרבנות korbanot to be brought
according to Rabbi. We'll see other opinions in a minute that you
do need the קרבנות korbanot to be brought. Okay. So ורב
יהודה ורב חסדא מאי דוחקיהו לאוקמה כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? v'Rav Yehuda
v'Rav Chisda mai douchkeihu l'oukma k'Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda? Now that we've
introduced this idea that for
Rabbi, it starts even that what that it restarts even if you
don't bring the קרבנות, korbanot, why did you have to say that
interesting ברייתא braita about multiple טומאות tumot and one קרבן korban was
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda? What we just said
a minute ago.
לוקמה, loukma, why not
say, כגון
דנטמא דחזיא בליל
שמיני ורבי היא? k'gon dentma d'chazya b'leil shmini v'Rabbi hi? So it
says look, I've got here's a solution, okay, in order to make
this work for Rabbi nontrivial and true. Let's say what happens is
remember, in order for it to be you to be
טהור, tahor, you to restart for Rabbi you have to enter into
day eight, right? Is that so? The idea that you became טמא
tamei multiple times would only be an interesting case if you restarted
the counting. And for Rabbi it needs day eight to restart the
counting. But we need to be a period where you've restarted the
counting but you're not yet obligated in a קרבן. korban. So what
is that case? So he says well look, day eight is divided
into two parts. There's night and there's day. The קרבן korban is
only comes at the day. You only bring קרבנות korbanot at the
day. But as soon as you enter into day eight at night,
the night leading into day eight, you have began day eight. And
Rabbi says when you begin day eight you don't need a קרבן
korban yet. When you begin day eight you begin the recounting. Right?
Everybody with me here? For Rabbi you entered into day eight. He
just told us the קרבן korban isn't necessary to start the recounting.
You started. It is 6:01 PM going into day eight. You now
have begun your new thirty days of נזירות. nezirut. Day eight began.
So you have restarted here. Okay, you restart on day eight. You're
טהור. tahor. You were טהור tahor on day seven, but anyway, but
you restart at the nighttime. Now you became טמא. tamei. So that
is exactly the case we were looking for. You've restarted your counting
because you're in day eight, you became טמא, tamei, so everything had
been restarted and you became טמא, tamei, and nevertheless you're not going
to bring another קרבן korban because you have not yet started the
daytime of day eight. You've not yet entered the time when you're
חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. So since everything was able to
be restart and re-טמא tamei without yet being חייב chayav in a
קרבן, korban, that would be a scenario where you could have multiple
טומאות tumot and only one קרבן. korban. Clear? Yeah? Okay, good. So
That's גמרא, Gemara, why not? Now we have a great way that
that works for רבי Rebbe as well. אי דלא ide lo so
לוקמה כגון דנטמא דחזי בליל
שמיני lukma k'gon d'nitma d'chazi baleil shmini that you were fit on
the night of the eighth, so the whole counting had restarted then
according to רבי, Rebbe, and you became, and then you became טמא,
tamei, and nevertheless only one קרבן korban because it's not yet the
daytime and you're not yet חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. So
רבי, Rebbe, and this goes like רבי. Rebbe. מדלא מוקי לה כרבי,
mid'lo moki lah k'Rebbe,
since you did not say that that was what was going on
and you didn't make it work like רבי, Rebbe, לימא קסבר לילה
לאו מחוסר זמן הוא. leima kasavar laila lav mechusar zman hu. The
only reason not to say this is because you hold that nighttime
is not considered lacking in time, מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman. What does
that mean? So what it means is, it's a classic question by
קרבנות, korbanos, which is
the night before something is to be brought or fit to be
brought, is it considered like its time has arrived yet? Okay, so
that's like interesting for various הלכות, halachos, let's say I slaughter an
animal, an animal is only fit on day eight, let's say I
slaughter it at night, not in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's
not a כשר kosher קרבן, korban, but let's say I don't know,
I bring it as a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, okay? I'm only חייב chayav for bringing a קרבן korban outside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if it's fit to be brought in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Or let's say I bring it the
night before. Is it fit to be brought in the בית—how Beis
did you know, do you define the period of the night before
as it's already fit to be brought, it's just you have to
wait a few more hours, right? How much is it that the
time has already come in some broader conceptual way even though it's
not yet the exact time to bring it? But the day is
here and that's enough. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is,
why not say this was a brilliant way that this ברייתא braisa
works for רבי? Rebbe? So the only reason not to say this,
and we're talking about day eight began, you became טהור, tahor, you
became טמא, tamei, everything you know restarted, became טמא tamei and nevertheless
you're not חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, you know why you wouldn't
say that? Because you would say no, no, no, if the nighttime
entered, you're already חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. You can't bring
it until the day, but you're חייב chayav in a קרבן korban
when the day begins, right? So then it once again doesn't work
like רבי, Rebbe, because once you're חייב chayav in a קרבן, korban,
then you'd have to bring another one, right? Everybody remembers that's the
setup. You've got to create a setup where you totally have restarted
the process of נזירות טהרה, nezirus taharah, but you're not yet חייב
chayav in a קרבן. korban. So גמרא Gemara says, well we've got
the example: the night of eight. It says ah, it must be
since you didn't give that answer, that you understand that actually you
are חייב chayav in a קרבן korban the night of eight. You
can't bring it until the daytime, but you're already חייב chayav the
night of eighth. Okay, so מדלא
מוקי לה כרבי mid'lo moki lah k'Rebbe since you didn't give that
answer, לימא קסבר לילה לאו מחוסר זמן הוא. leima kasavar laila lav
mechusar zman hu. It must be that the nighttime is not considered
lacking in time, meaning at some conceptual level you're already חייב chayav
in a קרבן korban on the night of eight. So can I
prove that that's your position? Okay רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, it's רב
חסדא Rav Chisda here, right? Yes. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, can I
prove that's your position that you say that night is considered the
time that it's fit to bring a קרבן, korban, not technically fit,
but it's that time, time already. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה הא בהא תליא. Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava
ha b'ha talya. No, there—those two ideas are dependent one on the
other. What does that mean? It's a great phrase, הא בהא תליא.
ha b'ha talya. That's like one of those rabbinic phrases that gets
used like all the time in ישיבה yeshiva speak. Okay. All right,
הא בהא תליא, ha b'ha talya, what do you mean—what is dependent
on the other? They're interdependent. אי אמרת לילה מחוסר זמן, i amrat
laila mechusar zman, if you say nighttime is considered to be not
yet the time for the
קרבן, korban, so אימת מטי לקרבן לצפרא, eimas mati l'korban l'tsafra, so
when is the time that's considered the time of the קרבן? korban?
Morning. So נזירות נמי לא חיילא עד צפרא. nezirus nami lo chayla
ad tsafra. So it also would only restart the נזירות nezirus in
the morning. ואי אמרת לילה אינו מחוסר זמן, v'i amrat laila eino
mechusar zman, and if you say that nighttime is the time of
a קרבן, korban, if nighttime is a time of a קרבן, korban,
so נזירות טהרה חיילא מאורתא, nezirus taharah chayla m'orta, so then it
starts at nighttime. Which means what? It means you thought the only
way you tried to get this idea to work of night and
day was you thought you would find, what is this like? This
is like this whole issue of, I don't know why I'm going
to say this example, like of arbitrage, where it's like you find
when the market's a little bit out of sync and you exploit
that advantage, right? So here you only thought you would find an
example where something was like out of sync, where like you would
restart the נזירות nezirus because it's the day eight, but you're not
yet חייב chayav in a קרבן korban because it's the night because
the day eight began, it's nighttime, but you're not yet חייב chayav
in a קרבן korban because it hasn't been daybreak. So the גמרא
Gemara says you can't do it. הא בהא תליא. ha b'ha talya.
The reason your נזירות nezirus restarts on day eight is because we
say that day eight is the time when it's fit to bring
a קרבן. korban. So if you say conceptually by night we're already
calling it the time of the קרבן, korban, then your נזירות nezirus
would restart at night. Okay, so then it would be a time
where yes, your נזירות nezirus would restart, but yes, you'd already be
חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. If we say that you're not
considered חייב chayav in a קרבן korban until the daytime, then your
נזירות nezirus doesn't restart until the daytime either, so you can't find
that place where they're not in sync. Right? Everybody gets it? Right,
according to this idea. The חידוש chidush is find a way in
which your נזירות nezirus has restarted and you became טמא, tamei, but
you're not yet חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, well, can't we find that in the nighttime of
day eight for רבי? Rebbi? And the גמרא Gemara says no. I
don't it doesn't matter what I hold about whether I consider the
nighttime to be the time of the קרבן korban or not. Either
way this answer isn't going to work. If the nighttime is the
time of the קרבן, korban, then then you'd be then
that would be true, you'd restart your נזירות nezirus at night, but
then you'd already be חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. And if
the nighttime wasn't the time of the קרבן, korban, then you wouldn't
restart your נזירות nezirus at night, you'd only restart your נזירות nezirus
in the day. So you're not the reason you restart your נזירות
nezirus is because it's considered the time to bring the קרבן, korban,
and you're never going to have this place where they're out of
sync. Okay, so that was a lot of fun,
I thought it was.
Okay. All right, so now we've got this debate. Is it day
seven or is it day eight? And according to רבי, Rebbi, it's
day eight, but day eight only because day eight is the time
to bring the קרבן. korban. So whether it's night of eight or
day of eight depends on what you think about the status of
night in terms of bringing קרבנות. korbanot. But it's but it works
without the קרבן, korban, but because it's considered the time of the
קרבן. korban. And now the גמרא Gemara goes ahead and wants to
explore other positions. So we have a position that starts on day
seven, restarts, one that it restarts on day eight because it's the
time of the קרבן korban even if you haven't brought a קרבן,
korban, and now we're going to see a few positions that it
only starts on day eight after the קרבנות korbanot have been brought,
which is maybe the most simple sense of the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay,
so let's take a look.
גופא, Gufa, let's go back and look at what we've been discussing.
נטמא בשביעי וחזר ונטמא בשביעי אינו מביא אלא קרבן אחד. Nitma beshvii
vechazar venitma beshvii eino meivi ela korban echad. So again, if seven
and seven, it's only one
קרבן. korban. נטמא בשמיני וחזר ונטמא בשמיני מביא קרבן על הכל. Nitma
bishmini vechazar venitma bishmini meivi korban al hakol. Okay, so it was
on the eighth day and then you became טמא tamei again on
the eighth day, this is something we said before, right? Then it
would only be, wait a minute, hold on. Right, then it would
be one קרבן korban for every act of becoming טמא tamei because
you would have already entered into day eight and already been obligated
in a קרבן. korban. I'm sorry, מביא קרבן על כל אחד ואחד.
Meivi korban al kol echad ve'echad. I'm sorry, I didn't end the
sentence right. מביא קרבן על כל אחד ואחד. Meivi korban al kol
echad ve'echad. Okay, now fine, that's what we said about this issue
about multiple קרבנות korbanot or one קרבן, korban, but that's really not
our interest. Here's what our interest is. When do you restart? You
okay there? So when do you restart? מתחיל ומונה מיד. Matchil umoneh
miyad. So you restart immediately, which is presumably means we said you
restart on day eight, but immediately on day eight. דברי רבי אליעזר.
Divrei Rebbi Eliezer. Now our גירסא girsa here is דברי רבי אליעזר.
Divrei Rebbi Eliezer. There's a problem with that because of רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer in the משנה, Mishnah, and I'm just going to simplify
all this and go by the גר״א. Gra. And the גר״א Gra
takes out the word אליעזר Eliezer and he has it as דברי
רבי, Divrei Rebbi, and it really makes everything read a lot easier
because we've already introduced רבי Rebbi to say that you restart on
day eight. Okay, so we've said yes, you know, you restart on
day eight, day eight is the day of bringing the קרבן, korban,
okay, but מיד, miyad, even without having brought the קרבן. korban. דברי
רבי, Divrei Rebbi, that's what רבי Rebbi says. וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim,
but the sages say, קרבן אחד על הכל עד שיביא חטאתו. Korban
echad al hakol ad sheyavi chatato. No, it's not that you become
obligated in the קרבן korban as soon as you know it restarts
and you become obligated etc. on day eight
automatically. No, you're it's you'll bring one קרבן korban and everything, which
is a way of signifying that it hasn't yet restarted, right? If
you only bring one קרבן, korban, we've been saying that that means
that the whole process hasn't restarted. So they're saying you're only going
to bring one קרבן korban until עד שיביא חטאתו, ad sheyavi chatato,
until you bring your חטאת. chatas. הביא חטאתו ונטמא הביא חטאתו ונטמא
מביא על קרבן על כל אחד ואחד. Heivi chatato venitma heivi chatato
venitma meivi al korban al kol echad ve'echad. You bring a קרבן
korban on each one. So this is a little confusing because rather
than just saying black and white when do you restart the counting,
it's framing it in terms of one קרבן korban or multiple קרבנות.
korbanot. So let me just take a step back and again say
it like this. For רבי, Rebbi, right, if you become טמא tamei
on day eight, you know, then you bring a multiple you know,
you became טהור tahor and whatever on day seven, day eight you
became טמא tamei again, you'll bring multiple קרבנות. korbanot. Why? Because he
would say as soon as day eight began, even without having brought
any קרבן, korban, you've restarted your process, you've restarted your נזירות, nezirus,
so another becoming טמא tamei would be another obligation of a קרבן,
korban, right? That's what רבי Rebbi says. Okay, comes along this next
opinion, who is it? חכמים, Chachamim, and they say no. Your נזירות
nezirus doesn't begin, your recounting doesn't begin just because day eight began.
Your recounting only begins once you bring your חטאת. chatas. Now again
to remind you, there are two birds, one's an עולה, olah, one's
a חטאת, chatas, and then there's an אשם, asham, which is like
a lamb, okay, but we're focusing on the חטאת. chatas. So what
they are saying is, now they could have just said it more
simply. Let's say you're a normal נזיר, nazir, again we're at the
stage where we're just talking about a normal נזיר. nazir. You're a
normal נזיר, nazir, normal case, you're a נזיר, nazir, you became טמא,
tamei, okay, you became טהור tahor on day seven and day eight
you were lazy and you didn't get around to bring your חטאת.
chatas. When do you start your counting? According to רבי, Rebbi, day
eight. According to this opinion... only the day you bring your חטאת.
chatas. So we could have just had a simple debate: when do
you restart your counting? רבי Rebbi says on day eight. The other
opinion says no, only once you get around to bringing your חטאת.
chatas. But the way we're framing it is, let's say you didn't
bring your חטאת chatas on day eight and you became טמא tamei
on day eight, would you have to now bring two sets of
קרבנות? korbanos? Now don't tell me you already brought your first set
because you only brought your חטאת, chatas, there's also an עולה olah
and an אשם, asham, okay, so saying multiple sets is a whole
group of קרבנות korbanos you would have to bring. So רבי Rebbi
would say, yeah, of course you have to bring multiple קרבנות, korbanos,
you already restarted your counting. And the חכמים chachamim would say no,
since you didn't bring your חטאת, chatas, you didn't restart your counting,
and since you didn't restart your counting, you don't have to bring
another set of קרבנות. korbanos. But let's say on day eight you
brought your חטאת chatas but you didn't bring your עולה olah and
you didn't bring your אשם asham and then you became טמא. tamei.
Ah, once you brought your חטאת, chatas, you did restart your counting,
and now if you became טמא, tamei, it's a new obligation and
a whole new set of קרבנות. korbanos. Okay? Everybody clear? So the
question about multiple קרבנות korbanos or one קרבן korban just reflects the
question of have you restarted your counting. רבי Rebbi says you restart
your counting on day eight, so if you become טמא tamei anytime
on day eight, you have restarted your counting, you became טמא tamei
again, a new set of קרבנות. korbanos. And the חכמים chachamim say
you do not restart your counting until you bring your חטאת. chatas.
So if you became טמא tamei before bringing your חטאת, chatas, it's
all the same process, no extra קרבנות. korbanos. If you brought your
חטאת, chatas, then you restarted your counting, it's a new process, now
you would do another set of קרבנות. korbanos. So let's read that
again. וחכמים אומרים קרבן אחד על הכל עד שיביא חטאתו, Vachachamim omrim
korban echad al hakol ad sheyavi chataso, until you bring your חטאת,
chatas, because then you haven't restarted your counting until you bring your
חטאת. chatas. הביא חטאתו ונטמא הביא חטאתו ונטמא Heivi chataso venitma, heivi
chataso venitma seven, eight days later, מביא קרבן על כל אחד ואחד.
meivi korban al kol echad ve'echad. After you've brought your חטאת, chatas,
then you restart your counting, and if then you became טמא, tamei,
that would be an obligation of another set of קרבנות. korbanos. Okay,
so that's the position of, so we got a position of רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda day seven, we have a
position of רבי Rebbi day eight, night time of day eight or
daytime of day eight depends on when you think is the time
of the קרבן, korban, but day eight, when the time of the
קרבן korban arrives. And now we have the position of the חכמים
chachamim that say you only restart your counting when the חטאת chatas
is brought. Okay, now,
הביא חטאתו ולא הביא אשמו מונה. Heivi chataso velo heivi ashamo moneh.
But if you brought your חטאת, chatas, even if you haven't gotten
around to bringing your אשם, asham, once you bring your חטאת, chatas,
you still start recounting. That's the position of the חכמים. chachamim. רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, Rebbi Yishmael beno shel
Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, and רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael the son
of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka
says no, כשם שחטאתו עכבתו, keshem shechataso ikvato, the same way your
חטאת chatas holds you back from restarting,
כך אשמו מעקבו. kach ashamo me'akvo. So bringing your אשם asham holds
you back from restarting. These are things, a חטאת chatas and an
אשם asham are classic קרבנות korbanos that are part of a טהרה
taharah process, like if somebody is, I don't know, a מצורע metzora
or a זבה zavah or any types of cases or זב zav
that you bring קרבנות korbanos to become טהור, tahor, חטאת chatas and
אשם asham are the קרבנות korbanos that are mostly involved and mostly
seen as necessary for part of that transition change of status process.
So רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbi Yishmael beno
shel Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka says you don't get to restart until
you've brought all the central קרבנות. korbanos. Maybe not the עולה, olah,
עולה olah is always seen as a little bit extra, not central
to the טהרה taharah process, but until you bring your חטאת chatas
and your אשם, asham, you don't get to restart your counting. It's
not enough to bring your חטאת. chatas.
כשם שחטאתו עכבתו כך אשמו מעקבו. Keshem shechataso ikvato kach ashamo me'akvo.
Okay, so now we have two new positions, let's look at them.
בשלמא לרבי אליעזר, Bishlama leRebbi Eliezer, we get רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
that says that you need to, which one is רבי? Rebbi? Oh,
actually it could be לרבי, leRebbi, we're going with the גרסא Girsa
version. It's good according to רבי Rebbi that says you automatically start
on day eight, אמר קרא וקידש את ראשו ביום ההוא, amar kra
vekidesh es rosho bayom hahu, which is what we said before, that
day, regardless of whether you brought the קרבנות korbanos or not, אף
על פי שלא הביא קרבנותיו. af al pi shelo heivi korbonosav. So
that works, day eight, fine, we got that. We got the position
of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda day seven, we
got רבי's Rebbi position of day eight without any קרבנות, korbanos, once
the time of the קרבן korban arrives. And now let's look at
these two new positions. ולרבנן, Ulerabbanan, what would the rabbis say? No,
ההוא אף על פי שלא הביא אשמו. hahu af al pi shelo
heivi ashamo. ביום ההוא Bayom hahu tells you yes, that day, the
day itself is significant, which means you don't have to bring all
your קרבנות. korbanos. That I'll agree, but you still have to bring
the central one, you still have to bring the חטאת. chatas. Without
the חטאת, chatas, you can't start counting again.
אלא, Ela, so we get that, they both have the emphasis of
the פסוקים pesukim on the קרבן korban and the ביום ההוא, bayom
hahu, and the compromise is, or the way it works out, is
you have to bring your חטאת chatas even if you didn't bring
your עולה. olah. אלא רבי ישמעאל, Ela Rebbi Yishmael, according to רבי
ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, who he reads the פסוקים pesukim after all the
קרבנות korbanos you get to restart, that might work in terms of
a simple sense of the פסוקים, pesukim, but ההוא למה לי? hahu
lama li? When it says that day, that suggests the day itself
is important even without all the קרבנות. korbanos. So how do you
explain that if you say you need to bring all the קרבנות
korbanos to restart? So אמר
לך, amar lach, he would say to you,
ההוא אף על פי. hahu af al pi. No, it is significant,
the day. You don't need all your קרבנות. korbanot. If you bring
your חטאת chatat and your אשם, asham, even if you didn't bring
your עולה, olah, you're still okay. But you need to bring the
central קרבנות korbanot in order to restart. So that's probably the simplest
sense of the פסוק, pasuk, that you need to bring the קרבנות
korbanot before restarting. And all he gives, and all he does with
ההוא hahu is to say, okay, you don't have to bring the
עולה. olah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומניתא, u-manya,
ורבנן, ve-rabanan, and what would the rabbis say? Why don't they read
it that way? That all it's doing is saying the עולה olah
isn't important. עולה לא בעי מיעוטא. olah lo baei miuta. No, no,
no. You didn't need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that the
עולה olah was not central to this process. דורון בעלמא הוא, doron
be-alma hu, it's just a gift. Okay? An עולה olah is something
that's a free-will sacrifice that you can, anybody can donate an עולה.
olah. And it is never seen as a central part of a
טהרה tahara process or a change of status process. That's always the
חטאת chatat and the אשם. asham. Okay, so מאי טעמייהו דרבנן? mai
taamaihu de-rabanan? Now, let's look a little bit more closer in the
פסוקים. pesukim. What's, where do the rabbis, how do they read the
פסוקים pesukim to say a חטאת chatat is required to restart, but
you know, not, but it's not enough to be the day itself.
דתניא, de-tanya, ותני על הפסוק, ve-tani al ha-pasuk, והזיר לה' את ימי
נזרו. ve-hizir l'Hashem et yemei nizro.
It says you bring your two birds, your חטאת chatat and your
עולה, olah, and you dedicate to Hashem the days of your נזירות.
nezirot. והביא, ve-hevi, and after saying you dedicate the days of your
נזירות nezirot after having brought the חטאת chatat and the עולה, olah,
then it says, והביא כבש בן שנתו לאשם, ve-hevi keves ben shenato
le-asham, a lamb for an אשם. asham. מה תלמוד לומר? ma talmud
lomar? So what's the significance of this order? לפי שמצינו שכל אשמות
שבתורה שאין מעכבין. lefi she-matzinu she-kol ashamot she-ba-Torah she-ein me'akvin. We normally
do find that yes, an אשם asham is central to a process
of טהרה tahara when קרבנות korbanot are part of that process of
טהרה tahara and to a change of status process. Normally the אשם
asham is central to that process when you need a קרבן korban
to change status. יכול אף זה מעכבו? yakhol af ze me'akvo? So
I might have, I would have assumed reasonably the same would be
true here. You can't restart your נזירות nezirot until you bring your
אשם. asham. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches, והזיר והביא. ve-hizir
ve-hevi. You should dedicate, rededicate the days, meaning restart the counting, and
then bring the אשם. asham. אף על פי שלא הביא הזיר. af
al pi she-lo hevi hizir. The dedication, the נזירות nezirot began even
before the אשם asham was brought. It's just a simple sequence of
the פסוקים. pesukim. It says you bring your חטאת chatat and then
you, you re-become a נזיר, nazir, you restart your נזירות nezirot of
טהרה tahara and then you bring your אשם. asham. So here you
do not need the אשם asham to restart the process. Nice read
of the פסוקים. pesukim. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
אומר, Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, now here's
what Rabbi Yishmael would say.
והזיר והביא, ve-hizir ve-hevi, here's how he reads the פסוק. pasuk. You
shall become a נזיר nazir or you know, restart the נזירות nezirot
and bring.
אימתי הזיר? eimatai hizir? When do you restart the נזירות? nezirot? בזמן
שהביא, bi-zman she-hevi, when you have brought. Okay? So it doesn't mean
first you restart your נזירות nezirot and then you bring. והזיר והביא,
ve-hizir ve-hevi, you'll restart your נזירות nezirot finally once you finish this
process and bring your אשם. asham. That's when you'll restart your נזירות.
nezirot. Okay, so we have fascinatingly we've got four opinions when a
נזירות nezirot of טהרה tahara restarts after becoming טמא. tamei. One is
day seven, because that's the day you became טהור. tahor. That's רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Yehuda. One is רבי, Rabbi, day
eight, because that's the day when you were ready to bring the
קרבן korban and the פסוק pasuk says ביום ההוא. ba-yom hahu. As
long as it's the time of קרבן, korban, that's enough. Is it
the night? Is it the day? That depends on your general question
of what do you think about the night before a קרבן korban
is brought. And then you have these two positions: the חכמים Chachamim
that say no, the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is you
bring your birds, your חטאת chatat and your עולה, olah, the כהן
Kohen atones, and then you restart your נזירות. nezirot. So maybe the
עולה olah isn't central because עולה olah is never central to the
process, but without the חטאת chatat you don't restart your נזירות. nezirot.
And finally רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael
beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says you got to bring both
the חטאת chatat and the אשם. asham. The one thing I'll be
מוחל mochel on is the עולה, olah, but you know, he's going
to read the פסוקים pesukim to say you got to do the
whole קרבן korban because only then do those types of קרבנות korbanot
are central to the טהרה tahara and, not to טהרה, tahara, but
to the change of status process and to restarting the נזירות. nezirot.
Okay, so now what, because we have an extra minute or two,
actually we have a lot of extra time. I should have prepared
ahead because we're not going to have too much time on ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but I do want to read to you, it's
unfortunately that דב Dov isn't here, he would really appreciate this. I
want to read to you an interesting תוספות Tosafot on יח עמוד
ב, yud-chet amud bet, which is right before the, the end of
the narrow side, most narrow lines. איכא דאמרי דגרסי בה. ika d'amri
de-garsi beh. Okay, so you see that, that little תוספות Tosafot there?
So there's some גמרות Gemarot like when we introduced this whole debate
about which קרבנות korbanot you have to bring to be restarted, it
started with גופא. gufa. It started with, let's say the גופא, gufa,
let's go back and look at what we discussed before. ונתמי בשמיני
ve-nitma ba-shmini etcetera and it quoted that whole thing about becoming טמא
tamei on the seventh day, eighth day, do you restart, etcetera. So
תוספות Tosafot says, לא גרסינן, lo garsinan, we don't have that word
גופא gufa in here. Why? דבכולה ש"ס, de-be-kholah Shas, in all of
the ש"ס, Shas, לא גרסינן גופא, lo garsinan gufa, the word גופא
gufa is only used אלא כשהביא מימרא או ברייתא תחילה, ela keshe-hevi
memra o baraita techila, when the גמרא Gemara first brought a type
of a, you know, אמורא-ic Amora statement or a ברייתא, Baraita, והביא
אותה אגב גרירא ve-hevi otah agav grira and brought it in passing,
in part of a, the debate to prove one side of the
debate, so it brought in some
ברייתא. Baraita. And then after having brought it in as part of
a debate, it says, you know what, let's go back to the
body of that text and analyze it in more depth, לפרש המימרא
או הברייתא. L'faresh hamemra o habraita. So interesting to have תוספות Tosafot
reflect on the technical use of the word גופא. Gufa. We brought
something in in passing; let's go back and look at the body
of that text and analyze it more deeply.
אבל ברייתא לא הביא אשכח כלל אלא מלישנא דשס. Aval braita lo
heivi ashkeich klal ela milishana d'shas. Here, it's not quoting a ברייתא;
braita; it's not even quoting a מימרא memra of אמוראים. Amoraim. It's
quoting a סתם stam of the גמרא. Gemara. It's re-referring to its
own סתם stam language: אילמא שנתנה מפתיחתא. Ilema shenitna mipetichta. So why
use the word גופא? Gufa? Because it's not quoting an earlier text
like a ברייתא braita or a מימרא; memra; it's just quoting its
own שקלא וטריא, shakla v'tarya, its own language. Okay, but it's really
nice, his key point here is that you only use גופא Gufa
on a ברייתא braita or a מימרא, memra, not on referring to
the very סתם stam of the גמרא Gemara itself. But what's more
impressive to me is he framed it: look, here's how it's used,
something is brought in passing and now we're going to go back
and look at it fully and look at it in greater depth.
Okay, that's the difference between גופא Gufa and אמר
מר Amar Mar because גופא Gufa is—and let's see if I get
this right—גופא Gufa is as תוספות Tosafot says: you might have quoted
the whole ברייתא, braita, but it was quoted only to extract a
little point and to make a small point about it, and now
you want to really get into it in depth. אמר מר Amar
Mar is when you just quote a line from a text and
now that we're done with our discussion, now we're going to quote
the full text. So
אמר מר Amar Mar is the same type of an idea—we're going
to go back to a text—but אמר מר Amar Mar is now
we only quoted one line, now we're going to quote the full
one. גופא Gufa is we quoted the full one but now we
want to look at it in depth and not just in passing.
All right, so we will end here and see you all tomorrow.
Okay, yep. Have a nice night. How often does תוספות Tosafot quote
this? Is it so rare to have תוספות Tosafot every day?
Well, I don't know, but the point is there's a one...